好的，谢谢大家的到来。
Okay. Thanks for coming.
好，我们继续。后勤更新。
Yeah, let's resume. Logistic update.
下节课在周四，我们会有一位嘉宾讲者，
Next lecture, Thursday, we'll have our guest speaker,
你们不必到现场，只需要在Zoom上参加，我们的嘉宾在我看来，
you don't have to be here, just go attend on Zoom, our speaker was, in my opinion,
是唯一真正做开源语言模型的人。
the only guy that is truly doing open language models.
因为你们知道，在语言模型社区有很激烈的争论。
Because you know, there's a strong debate in the language model community.
你怎么定义“开源”？
What do you define by open?
你说的开源是什么意思？比如你发布了语言模型的权重，你可以称之为open Ws，
What do you mean by open? Like if you release language model weights, you can call it open Ws,
但你不能称之为开源。为什么？
but you cannot call it open source. Why?
因为别人无法用算力复现。
Because people cannot reproduce with with compute.
你要如何发布你的数据、你的基础设施、你的训练方法，
You how to release your data, your infrastructure, uh, your training recipe, and
还有你的权重，这样别人才能复现你的成果。
your weights so people can reproduce.
所以在周四，我们的演讲嘉宾就是一个基本上什么都公开的人，好吗？
So on Thursday, our speaker is a guy who basically release everything, okay?
权重、数据、基础设施、代码检查点，每一个检查点都公开了。
Weights, data, um, infrastructure, code checkpoints, every checkpoint.
这就是为什么这个项目叫做RM 360，因为他们发布了60个检查点，
That's why the project is called RM 360, because they release 60 checkpoints
方便你去复现，好吗？
for you to reproduce, okay?
听完他的演讲后，你们可以思考一下，这到底意味着什么，
And you guys after listening to his talk, you can think about what is so what
其实RM的事情就是在做开源。
is basically RM thing is going in open source.
那我们应该像OpenAI那样拥抱闭源模型，还是应该支持开源模型？
So should we embrace close models like open eyes or should we embrace open model?
好好想想这个问题。嗯，我们回来继续。
Yeah, think about that. Okay. Um, let's come back.
我记得上周四我们讨论了连接通信，对吧？
I think, last Thursday, we talked about connective communication, right?
我觉得我们不知不觉就讲到这里了，对吧？
And I think we somehow arrive here, right?
所以我们把连接通信和机器学习中的并行方式联系在一起了，
So we connect connective communication with our machine learning parallelisms,
对吧，特别是内部并行。
right, especially intra parism.
我们发现，在机器学习的并行中，我们必须做这种重新分布的操作，
And we find that in machine learning parallelism, we have to do this kind of recharting
而重新分布的代价本质上就是连接通信。
and the cost of recharging is essentially connective.
并且根据你如何进行重新分布，比如你从行分布切换到列分布，或者你切换
And depending on how you do recharting you switch from role pating common parting or you switch
从复制到行分布，你会遇到不同类型的连接通信，对吧？
from replicated to row patting, you are going to have different sorts of connective, right?
所以在这里，如果你切换……不好意思。
So here, if you switch from sorry.
如果你从分片切换到复制，你就必须在两个设备之间做全量收集。
If you switch from parts to replicate it, you have to do or gather right across two devices.
这是一个部分和。
And this is a partial sum.
我想上周我错过了这一部分，但我在这里加上了。
I think in last week, I missed this part, but I added here.
所以如果你想把它从部分和切换到复制模式，你就必须做归约，对吧？
So if you want to switch it from partial sum to replicated, you have to do or reduce, right?
好的。所以基本上，我们把通信连接和机制划分联系起来。
Okay. So basically, we connect connective communication with machinery partisms.
好的。接下来，我们要讨论各种划分方式，并且我们
Okay. Next, I'm going to so we are going to talk about all sorts of pisms and we
要把这些付诸实践，因为我觉得我已经花了足够的时间让你们
are going to put this in practice because I think I have spent enough time to give you to give you
理解划分的抽象概念，现在我要把它应用到实际中。
an understanding of pism at a very abstract level, and now I'm going to put it into practice.
好吗？我会用各种论文来说明，比如
Okay? I'm going to ground this with all different papers like people
别人发表的、用树模型的论文。
publish and people use tree models.
好的，我们将从数据划分开始。
Okay, we are going to start with data parism.
Why? You're probably wondering why because, like I said, data partism is
just a special case of intra partism, right?
But I still want to spend some dedicate time on data pism because,
first, it is one of the most adopted one, right?
Because no matter what kind of pism you are going to use, you always have data parism.
Second, as you know, big model is just a recent thing.
Before 2020, I don't think the models are that big, the motivation for motoparism
is because we want to train big models.
Our memory is insufficient.
But you need to remember in many cases, we have a small enough model that we can fit into one TPU.
那样的话，我们可能就不会采用任何形式的模型并行，因为那太复杂了。
In that case, we probably don't pursue any sort of motparism because it's too complicated.
我们想要的是尽可能简单的，数据并行就非常简单，而且能保证
We want something as simple, datapoism is really simple, it can guarantee to give you
在扩展时有相当不错的性能表现。
pretty good performance on scaling up.
好的，我们来简单回顾一下历史。
Okay, to review a little bit on history.
基本上2012到2016年，是深度神经网络变得非常流行的时期，对吧？
So basically 2012-2016, that's when Diplnary networks become very, um, popular, right?
实际上，在这篇论文中，这是由谷歌的Jeff Dean发表的。
And we actually, in this paper, which is published by Jeff Dino, from Google.
他们基本上构建了这个叫做Disbelief的框架。
And they basically build this, um, um, framework called disbelief.
这是第一个用于训练神经网络的分布式系统，好吗？
That is the first kind of, um, distributed system for training neural networks, okay?
这个系统采用的主要并行方式
And the palism that is adopted the primary palism that is adopted in
基本上就是数据并行，好吗？
the system is basically data pism, okay?
这是很早以前的事情，大概十五年以上了。
It's very early, like more than 15 years.
好的。从那篇论文之后，
Okay. And since that paper,
我认为在边缘计算社区的很多人，
I think a lot of people basically in the margining community,
机器学习加上Pism社区，他们基本上都在
Machine learning plus Pism community, they are basically just
研究数据并行，因为就像我说的，那时候多重并行还不是必须的，对吧？
studying datapoism because like I said, the multipoism is not necessary at that moment, okay?
所以人们发明了很多技术来让数据并行变得更好，对吧？
So people have invented a lot of techniques to make data parison better, okay?
我们接下来会讨论这些内容。
And we are going to talk about that.
然后你可能知道2016年Petrog发布了，对吧？
And then you probably know in 2016, Petrog was out, right?
而加入Petrot的第一个并行方式也是数据并行，
And the first partism that is added into Petrot is also data partism
因为它的用户最多，对吧？
because that has the most user, okay?
如果你看这段代码，嗯，你可能会注意到
And if you look at this piece of code, um, you'll probably notice
这个非常熟悉的接口，
this interface which is super familiar,
DDP分布式数据并行，它基本上就是数据并行的实现，呃，在Petrich中。
DDP distributed data parlo It is basically data per data pismimplementation in, uh, in Petrich.
而且，我在上一节课已经告诉过你，这个DDP在幕后基本上就是这样用的。
And, I already told you in my previous lecture, this DDP behind the scene is basically or use.
它就是这样用的，好吗？
I performs on use, okay?
是的，这个接口确实很不错，对吧。
Yeah, this interface is pretty good right.
我觉得这是Piper团队做得很好的地方。
That is, I think what Piper team did pretty well.
所以你需要做的其实就是用GDP把你的模型包裹起来
So what you need to do is essentially you just wrap your model with GDP
它就会自动变成数据并行，好吗？
and it automatically becomes data Parod, okay?
而且在某个时候，我觉得，我们也有很多开源框架在尝试
And at some point, I think, we also have a lot of open source frameworks that is trying to
优化通信和数据并行，本质上就是优化，让所有的分布式操作都变快。
optimize the communication and in data partism essentially optimizing, um, uh, D make allds fast.
我觉得这部分是你的作业，好吗？
I think that's part of your homework, okay?
你可能已经知道这些了，对吧。
And you've probably already known this right.
这是数据并行的早期解释，我们有四个节点，
This is early interpretation of data partism where we have four ranks and
我们基本上是把它们的结果、梯度进行合并。
we basically reduce their results, reduce their gradients, okay?
现在，如果你看这个，其实很简单，因为我会给你一个更深入的解释，
Now, if you look at this, it's pretty simple because I'll give you a deeper interpretation of
并行其实分为内部并行和外部并行。
partism which is intra and inter.
好的，把这个放在一个具体的场景下来说，
Okay. Um to put this into context, okay?
那什么是数据并行呢？
So what is data partism?
就像我说的，数据并行其实是优化并行的一种特殊情况，我们来用这个来说明。
Like I said, data partism is essentially a special case of opt partism let's use
我们的解释是对数据分区进行解释。
our interpretation to interpret data partism.
所以这就是数据分区。
So this is data partism.
我让你看这个大概二十秒，好吗？
I will let you look at this for maybe 20 seconds, okay?
好的。是的。我觉得如果你只看这部分，其实很简单，对吧？
Okay. Yeah. I think if you just look at this part, it's very easy, right?
而且我们已经多次讲解过这个了。
And we have been going through this many, many times.
这是这个图的前向部分，单层MLP。
So this is the forward part of this graph, single layer MLP.
抱歉，是两层MLP。
Sorry, two layers MLP.
好的，这部分就是我们多次解释过的数据部分。
Okay. And this part is this data part, how we explain many times.
我们做的基本上就是对数据进行分区。
What do we do is basically we do parti in the data.
对，我们在批处理中进行分区。
Right. We parting the batch di machine.
我们将其复制为可训练的宽度，然后直接前向传播
We replicate it to with trainable width, and then we just forward
一直到新的网络中。
all the way through the new network.
所以在这些箭头中没有任何通信。
So there's no communication in any of this arrow.
为什么？因为没有重新共享，对吧？
Why? Because there's no resharing, right?
每次我们计算共享机制时都会达成一致，
Every time when we compute the sharing mechanism agree,
好的，在两个设备之间，或者两个算子之间。
okay, between two devices, between two operators.
嗯，但我又增加了一点复杂性。
Um, but I add a little bit more complexity.
那就是，我还画出了Bro图，好吗？
That is, I also draw the Bro graph, okay?
问题出现在反向图上。
The problem happens at the back graph.
所以如果我们开始开发Bro图，这部分还是没问题的，对吧？
So if we start developing the Bro graph, this part is still good, right?
我们仍然进行分区。
We still do partition.
一旦我们得到了损失，我们就通过神经网络传递这个损失。
That is once we have the loss, wegate the loss through the neural network.
所以我们仍然只在指定的批处理设备上进行计算，对吧？
So we still like compute only on that designated batch device, okay?
但问题是当我们开始聚合梯度时，
But the problem is when we start aggregating the gradients,
我们发现这里有一个问题，就是这一部分，对吧，还有这一部分。
we find that there is a problem that is this part, right, and this part.
好的。所以当我们开始聚合梯度时，我们发现每个设备
Okay. So when we start aggregating gradits we find that E device
只有部分梯度，对吧？
only have a partial gradient, right?
但我们需要的是每个设备都拥有一份完整的梯度副本，这样我们
But what we need is we need each device to have a replica gradient so we
才能将梯度应用到参数上。
can apply the gradients to the parameters.
所以你已经知道这里会发生什么了，对吧？
So you already know what happens here, right?
或者减少，可以吗？
Or reduce Okay?
可以。我希望这种解释能让大家非常容易理解。
Yeah. I hope this interpretation makes this super easy to understand.
好的。在你应用分级之后，你基本上就有了一份新的权重副本，
Okay. And after you apply the gradings, you basically have a new copy of weights,
这些权重会在两个设备之间复制，然后你基本上在这里替换，
which are replicated across two devices, and you basically substite here,
你把它分配到这里，然后就完成了。
you assign to here, and you are good.
然后你开始下一代。
You start next generation.
好的，这个图有问题吗？
Okay. Any questions about this graph?
很好，非常好。我们在接下来的多并行部分会经常这样做。
Cool, very good. And we're going to do this a lot in following Multi pari section.
好的？那么你其实可以发现这里的关键变化，相比没有并行的时候，
Okay? So then you can actually spot that the key change here, compared to without pitism,
数据并行的关键变化其实就是我们如何实现这个先验，如何实现这个骰子。
the key change of data parism basically how we implement this prior, how we implement this dice,
我们如何实现一种非常高效的方法。
how we implement a very efficient way.
因为否则，剩下的基本上就是数据流图的执行，其他都不会变，对吧？
Because otherwise, all the rest is basically data flow graph execution, nothing changes, right?
好的。那么我们该如何实现这个呢？
Okay. So how do we implement this?
就像我说的，都是归约操作，但d有很多方法可以让它变快。
Like I said, it's all reduced, but d has um many ways to make it fast.
好吗？在历史上，有两种实现方式。
Okay? So in history, there are two ways to implement this.
第一种是非常著名的一篇论文。
The first is a very famous paper.
我认为第一种，比如说一篇著名的机器论文，叫做主服务器。
I would say the first, like a famous machine paper is called primary server.
好吗？第二种方式本质上都是归约。
Okay? The second way essentially all reduced.
好的，我们先来谈谈主服务器。
Okay? Let's talk about primary server first. Okay?
那么在主服务器中，嗯，不过对于这两种实现方式，
So in primary server, um, but for both implementation,
我认为他们懂得如何尊重，嗯，数据并行的关键假设。
I think they how to respect um the key assumption of
也就是说模型参数无法放入EDS，你可以用副本的方式处理。
data parism that is the model parameters can't fit into EDS, you can do that replica.
好的，对于主服务器来说，实际上主服务器出现得比
Okay, so for primary server, um, actually, the primary server comes much earlier
任何并行方式都要早得多。
than like any parallelism.
为什么？因为它甚至比神经网络还要早出现。
Why? Because it comes even earlier than neur networks.
为什么？因为主服务器是为分布式梯度下降而发明的。
Why? Because primary server was invented for doing distributed grading descent.
好的，但是你知道，在神经网络出现之前，我们已经有梯度下降了。
Okay. But, you know, before neural network, we already have grading descent.
我们可以用梯度下降来优化许多其他类型的模型，对吧？
We can use grading descent to optimize many other kinds of models, right?
所以我基本上想让你稍微改变一下思维方式。
So I want to basically um change your mindset a little bit.
现在，让我们把注意力放在梯度下降上，而不是神经网络。
Now, let's look at grading descent instead neuralnetwork.
好的。现在，这个模型可以是任何东西。
Okay. Now, this model can be anything.
如果你看梯度下降的话，对吧，这就是方程。
And if you look at grading descent, right, this is the equation.
我说这是主方程。
I said it's master equation.
在这里，相比之前的主方程，
And here, compared to the previous master equation,
我做的就是基本上加上了这个求和，对吧。
what I did is I basically add add this sum, right.
好的。那么有什么不同呢？
Okay. So what's the difference?
在我之前的写法中，
So in my previous writing,
我没有这个求和，所以我只有一个工作者。
I don't have the sum, so I only have one worker.
这里的P是工作者的索引。
So here P is a worker index.
好的，我有大写P个工作者。
Okay, I have capital P workers.
所以在我之前所谓的批量方程中，
So in my previous so called mass equation,
我只有一个工作节点来处理那批数据并计算梯度。
I just have one worker to work on that batch data and derived gradients.
但现在我要做的是加一个求和。
But now what I do is I add a sum.
也就是说，我有多个工作节点分别处理不同的批量数据，
That is, I have multiple workers to work on different batiel data to
并且并行地计算各自的梯度。
perform other gradients in parallel.
然后在某个时刻，
And at some point,
我会聚合它们的梯度，然后应用更新。
I'm going to aggregate their gradients, and then I apply the update.
明白了吗？这是主服务器。
Okay? This is the primary server.
呃，之所以叫主服务器，是因为你可以看到，
Uh, the reason is called primary server because you can see,
这是参数，这是梯度。
this is a parameter, and this is a gradients.
所以你基本上可以设计一个分布式系统，把参数放在某个服务器上。
So you can basically invent a distributed system where you put the parameters at some server.
你有很多工作节点来执行这个更新。
You have a lot of workers to perform this update.
一旦他们得到了梯度，这些工作节点就会把梯度发送到服务器。
And once they have the gradients, those worker is going to send the gradients to the server.
然后服务器会聚合梯度并应用更新，
And the server will aggregate gradients and then apply updates,
得到一个新的参数版本并发回去。
get a new version of parameter and send it back.
这就像是在做一个传统的分布式系统，
It's like doing a traditional distribute system,
对吧，就是一种服务器-工作节点的架构，叫做服务器架构。
right, a server work archicture call server archiecture.
好的，这其实很自然，对吧，因为如果你看这个公式，
Okay. Itis is pretty natural, right, because if you look at this equation,
你只是想要构建这样的系统。
you just want to build that system.
你觉得这个系统挺不错的，对吧？
You think that system is pretty good, okay?
嗯，这里有两个关于主服务器的关键假设。
Um, and there are two key, um, assumptions about primary server.
也就是说，它假设通信非常频繁。
That is, it assumes that the communication is very
计算与通信的比率是1210。
heavy and the compute to communication ratio is 1210.
我稍后会解释这一点。
So I will explain this later.
好的，但请记住这一点。为了说明这一点，基本上，这就是主服务器。
Okay but remember this. And to put this illustration, so basically, this is the primary server.
好吗？你可以看到有一个PS，也就是参数服务器，
Okay? You can see there's a PS which is the parameter server,
这是一个中心化的服务器，你可以在这里管理所有的工作节点。
centralized server, where you home manual workers.
每个工作节点基本上会取一批数据并计算梯度。
And each worker basically take a batch of data and compute the gradient.
一旦这里的梯度计算完成，
And then once the gradient is ready here, right,
每个工作节点都会把梯度发送到服务器。
each worker is going to send the gradient to server.
好的，服务器聚合更新后的参数，然后发送这个新参数
Okay, server aggregate updated parameter and then send this new parameter
回去，然后开始下一次迭代。
back and then start next iteration.
明白了吗？这很简单。
Okay? This is pretty easy.
那么这种架构有什么问题呢？
So what's the problem with this architecture?
有人想回答吗？好的。
Anyone want to answer? Yeah.
我猜有一个问题。对，没错。
I guess there's one. Yeah, exactly.
所以你可以看到主服务器变成了一个中心化的服务器，它需要
So you can see the primary server becomes a centralized server where it needs
接收所有类型的参数，这意味着你必须有
to receive all the kind of parameters, which means that you have to have
一个非常强大的服务器来接收来自许多工作节点的数据。
a very strong server to receive for many workers.
在这个图中，与其他工作节点的通信是四次。
Is communication is four times with other workers, in this figure four times.
但你可以想象，有很多很多的工作节点。
But you can imagine, there are many many workers.
然后，这个主服务器就会成为瓶颈。它会变得非常慢。
Then, this primary server becomes, bottleneck. It will be very slow.
第二，这个主服务器可能会成为单点故障。
Second, this primary server can be a single point failure.
比如如果这个主服务器故障了，我们就会丢失参数，
Like if this primary server failed, then we lose our parameters,
丢失梯度，我们需要重新开始。明白吗。
lose our gradients, we need to restart. Okay.
这显然不是可扩展的。
This is apparently not syllable.
但在我向你介绍更好的主服务器架构之前，
But before I present to you, better architectural primary serve,
呃，我想把这个和连接性联系起来。
uh, I want to basically connect this with connective.
所以如果你看这个，你只需要考虑通信。
So if you look at this one, uh, you just think about communication.
那么通信是什么？就像我说的，本质上他们是在做归约，对吧？
So what is the communication? Like I said, essentially they are doing or reduce, right?
但是这种架构是如何简化或者分解成不同的连接方式的呢？
But how this archiecture reduce or reduce into different connectives.
基本上在这个问题中，我们实际上是分解或者简化成两部分。
So basically in question, we basically decompose or reduce into two.
一部分被简化成一个。
One is reduced to one.
也就是说，我们从工作节点简化到服务器，然后再进行广播。
That is, we reduce from workers to server, and then we broadcast.
就像我在Max的讲座中说的，all reduce等于reduce加上broadcast。
So like I said, in Max lecture, all reduce equals to reduce plus broadcast.
好的，对吧？
Okay. Good, right?
所以，这就是这个思路。
So yeah, and this is the idea.
好的，我试着用连接方式来联系主服务器。
Okay. I try to connect primary server with connectives.
但就像我说的，主服务器S有几个原因导致它无法扩展。
But like I said, primary S is not scalable for a few reasons.
其中一个原因是主服务器是单点故障。
One is the primary server is a single point failure.
其次，主服务器S将会成为通信瓶颈。
Secondly, the primary S is going to become communication bottleneck.
那我们怎么能做得更好呢？
So how we can do better?
基本上，我们不一定非要有一个中心化的服务器。
So basically, we don't have to have a centralized server.
我们可以做一个分布式服务器。
We can do a distributed server.
但我们还可以进一步把主服务器切分成不同的工作节点，每个工作节点都变成一个服务器，
But we can further sharp the primary server into different workers and each worker become a server,
但只是服务器的一部分。
but a share of the server.
明白了吗？所以实际上，我们做的就是这种主服务器。
Okay? So basically in reality, what do we do is we do this kind of primary server.
我们有很多很多节点，有些节点只是服务器，有些节点是工作节点。
Many we have many many nodes, and some nodes are just servers and some nodes are workers.
在越来越多被采用的实际案例中，我们基本上做的是
And in a more and more adopted case, more real case, what do we do is basically we
让每个节点既是服务器又是工作节点。这样说有道理吗？
let each node to be a server and a worker. Does that make sense?
好的。每个节点既是服务器也是工作者本身。
Okay. That each node is a server and the worker itself.
它基本上会计算自己的那一份数据，同时还会存储
It will basically compute its own copy of ingredients, but it will also store
部分参数的中心化分片。
the centralized shard of part of the parameter.
好的，这样我们基本上就解决了中心化故障的问题，对吧？
Okay. In that way, we basically address that centralized failure problem, right?
因为现在每个节点、每个工作者、每个GPO都拥有一部分参数，
Because now each node, each worker, each GPO has a share of parameters,
他们基本上都要扮演服务器的角色。
and they need to basically play a role as a server.
他们需要连接，需要归约梯度，然后再广播梯度。
They need to connect they need to reduce gradients and and then broadcast gradients.
所有的边界、所有的GPO和设备都会被利用，对吧？
So all the bondaries all GPOs and devices will be utilized, right?
所以基本上，我们就把服务器的工作分散到了
So basically, we kind of, like, distribute the server's job into
很多很多不同的设备，比如互联网络。
many many different devices like interconnect networks.
好的。如果我这样做的话，想象一下极端情况，假如红色节点、
Okay. And if I do this, think about in extreme case, if basically the red nodes and
粉蓝色节点、蓝色设备和粉色设备其实都是同样的设备。
the pink blue nodes and blue devices and the pink devices are basically the same devices.
所以每个设备其实就是一个服务器本身，那么你能把这个和连接性联系起来吗？
So each device is basically a server work itself, then could you connect this to the connective?
所以我们还是在做同样的事情，但现在我们稍微改变了一点，对吧？
So we are still doing, but now we change a little bit, right?
基本上，现在我们首先要在所有节点之间执行一次reduce scatter操作。
So basically, it becomes we first perform a reduced scatter across all nodes.
因为现在每个节点都会持有参数的一个份额。
Because now each node will hold one share of the parameters.
所以每个工作节点都会持有自己梯度的完整副本，这意味着我们必须让
So each worker will hold a whole copy of its own gradient, which means that we have to let
每个工作节点把那一份梯度发送给持有那一份的服务器。
each worker to send that shard of um, gradients to server which holds that shard.
这就是reduce scatter操作。
This is a reduced scatter.
然后在reduce scatter之后，我们需要获得新参数的新副本，
And then after reduced scatter, we have to get a new copy of the new parameter,
这又是一个聚集操作。
which is another gather.
明白了吗？所以这个解释基本上是从之前的操作分解或简化而来的，
Okay? So this interpretation basically decompose or reduce from the previous one that
就是把简化的广播变成了简化的散播和聚集。
is reduced broadcast into reduced scatter and orgater.
你可以看到这种方式更好，因为它缓解了服务器的瓶颈问题。
And you can see this one is much better because it elevates the server bottleneck.
好，对这个有问题吗？
Okay. Any question about this one?
每个工作节点都是服务器，这不还是意味着只要有一个节点失败就会出问题吗？
Each worker is a server, doesn't that still mean that one worker fails?
就像合作关系，对吧？
Like partnership, right?
是的，非常好的问题。
Yeah. Very good question.
是的，所以每个工作节点仍然是服务器，如果那个节点失败了，
Yeah. So each worker is still a server, and if that worker failed,
那么共享的参数就会丢失，对吧？
then that shared parameter is going to be lost, right?
所以我们做的是让每个工作节点持有两个分片，一个作为备份。实际上，就是这样。
So what do we do is we a each worker to hold two shards, a backup. In reality, yeah.
这样你就可以降低某个分片完全丢失的概率，对吧？是的。
So you can reduce the probity that like a shard basically completely get lost, right? Yeah.
好的，这样说有道理吗？
Okay. Does that make sense?
很好，嗯，好的。
Cool. Um, okay.
然后我要告诉你一些更深入的内容。
And then I'm going to tell you something that is even deeper.
好的，如果你看这个，对吧，从这个讲解你可以看到，不，我们有几个工作节点，
Okay. So if you look at this one, right, from this speaker you can see, no, we have a few workers,
并且我们有一个主服务器。
and we have a primary server.
我们要做的是需要进行一次同步操作。
And what do we do is we need to do a synchronization operation.
就是每次每个工作节点完成梯度计算后，它必须把梯度发送给
That is every time we each worker finish the gradient calculation, it has to send the gradient to
服务器，服务器把它们聚合后再发回来。
the server server aggregate that and send it back.
但实际上，情况并不总是这样，因为你可能有不同的工作节点
But in reality, this is not always the case because you can have different workers that probably
有些工作节点可能会比其他工作节点慢。
some worker will be slower than other workers.
实际上你会遇到拖后腿的节点，对吧？
You have stragglers in reality, right?
可能是因为电源问题，也可能是因为你有不同类型的GPU，或者
It could be due to power issue could be due to, you have different kinds of GPUs or
只是某个程序比另一个程序运行得慢，对吧？
just that program runs slower than another program, right?
所以在这种情况下，你可以看到这个分布式系统会变得非常慢，对吧，
So in this case, you can see this distribute system will become extremely slow, right,
因为你必须从所有工作节点同步梯度，迭代的速度
because you have to synchronize the gradients from all workers, and the speed of iteration is
基本上是由这个组里最慢的工作节点决定的。
basically determined by the slowest worker in this group.
好的，这是个大问题。
Okay. That's a big problem.
这会引出我们下一个话题，
This will bring us into another,
我会说，这是一个非常非常活跃的研究领域。
I would say, very very active area of research.
也有人研究主服务器的一致性模型。
That is people also study consistency model for um primary servers.
有多少人了解分布式系统中的一致性模型？
How many of you know consistency model dist systems?
不，这其实就是一致性模型，基本上用来描述你应该在什么时候
No. Basically, that is a consist model, basic characterize when you should
在机器学习中同步你的梯度副本。
synchronize your copy gradients in machinearn.
这个图给你举了一个例子。
This figure give you an example.
你可以看到，我有三个设备，设备A、B和C，
You can see, I have three devices device A, B, and C,
每个设备都是一个工作节点，在某些时候它们需要通信，
EC device is a worker, at some point, they need to communicate,
就像我说的，在计算结束时。
like I said, at the end of competition.
所以这里我做了一个简化的假设，就是每个工作节点基本上都不会发生故障。
So here, I make a simplified assumption that is every worker will basically never have a fault.
他们永远不会犯任何错误。
They will never make any error.
程序会在每个工作节点上完美运行，而且每个人的进度都一致。
The program will run perfect on every worker and everyone will run in the same pace.
明白了吗？所以基本上按照上面的公式，我们每次做的事情是
Okay? So basically following above equation, what do we do is every time
每个工作节点都会计算梯度的副本，对吧？
each worker will calculate the copy of gradients, right?
然后他们会把梯度发送到主服务器，并且会等待，对吧？
And then they will send the gradits to the primary server, and they will wait, right?
他们会等待，因为他们必须等下一版参数被发送回来，
They will wait because they have to wait for the next version of parameter to be sent back to be
从服务器广播回来。所以他们会等待。
broadcast back from that server. So they will wait.
这个黑色的条基本上就是在等待。
And this black bars basically wait.
这叫做全局屏障。
It's called a global barrier.
好的。当所有工作节点都完成并收到新的参数副本后，
Okay. And once all the workers finish, receive the new copy of parameter,
他们基本上会开始下一轮计算，然后重复，他们会等待。
they will basically commence the next iteration of computer and they repeat, they will wait.
明白了吗？如果你的班级很完美，这个时间线看起来很酷。
Okay? And this timeline looks pretty cool, assuming that your class is perfect.
但实际上并不是这样，因为你会看到这个情况。
But in reality, that's not the case because in you will see this.
对吧？所以设备A就是比DSB慢。
Right? So device A is just slower than DSB.
USB是最快的，但DVI A稍微快一点。
USB is the fastest, but DVI A is a little bit faster.
如果你做这种类似全局屏障的操作，嗯，设备B，
And what you do is if you do this kind of like a global barrier, um, Device B,
基本上只用了一半的时间就完成了，对吧？
finish basically using half of the time, right?
但正如我说的，设备A非常慢。
But device A, like I said, is super slow.
所以基本上，B和C都得等A，对吧？
So basically, B and C how to wait for A, right?
因为他们必须等服务器聚合梯度并把新参数发回来。
Because they have to wait for the server to aggregate gradients and send the new parameter back.
好的，你可以看到这个被称为气泡。
Okay, you can see this is called it's called bubbles.
就像我说的，这是气泡。
Like I said, it's bubbles.
这是贡献信息系统中的气泡。
It's bubbles in the tribute system.
所以基本上，USB和其他设备在这个时候是在浪费钱。
And, so basically USB and are wasting money, at this time.
明白吗？而且其实在神经网络出现之前，这种情况很常见，
Okay? And people have this actually was pretty common before Neural Networks,
因为在神经网络出现之前，
because before New Networks,
我觉得很多模型有非常多的参数，但它们之间的通信带宽却很有限，
I think a lot of models they have so many parameters, but they don't have a lot of communication
你知道，在Spark和Maple那个时代，
bandwidth you know, back then in the area of Spark Maple produce,
人们会用很多异构节点来搭建集群。
people build clusters with a lot of heterogeneous nodes.
所谓异构，就是每个节点有不同类型的CPU和GPU，对吧？
But heterogeneous, I mean, each node has different kinds of CPU and GPU, right?
基本上是连接或者非常多样化的硬件配置
It's basically connection or very diverse hardware setups
而且每个设备实际上可以以不同的速度工作。
and each device can actually work with a different pace.
但今天不同了，因为现在人们正在建立一种超级计算中心，
But today is different because today now people are building kind of supercomputing center where you
基本上大家都用相同类型的GPU，这个问题就被提升了。
basically have the same type of GPU, this problem is kind of elevated.
但在那时候，这确实是事实，对吧？
But back then, this is true, okay?
所以那些人在思考的是，如何基本上减少这些“气泡”，对吗？
So what those people are thinking about is how to basically reduce these kind of bubbles, okay?
如何减少这些气泡。所以你可以看到，这就是一致性，对吧？
How to reduce the bubbles. So basically, you can see, this is the consistency, right?
这被称为强一致性，比如BSP。
This is called a strong consistency, like, BSP.
好的？我记得这叫做箱式同步一致性，
Okay? I think it's called a box synchronous consistency,
意思是所有的工作节点都必须等待，并且要以相同的速度同步。
Which means that all workers have to wait and how to be synchronized with the same pace.
但我们可以找到更好的方法，对吧。
But we can find something that's better, right.
我们可以稍微放宽一下这种一致性。
Red we can relax this consistency a little bit.
那么要怎么放宽呢？嗯，为什么我们不能放宽？
So how to relax. Um, so why we can't relax?
因为想想我们现在在做什么。
Because think about what we are doing here.
基本上，每个工作节点都在计算梯度副本，然后服务器试图聚合这些梯度。
So basically, every worker is computed copy gradients and the serve is trying to grade the gradients
然后执行梯度下降。
and then perform a grading descent.
我们可能都知道，分布式程序有一个很好的特点。
And we probably know that marcheering programs they have a very nice characteristic.
那就是它对错误有很强的容忍性。
That is it is very error tolerant.
那么什么叫做对错误有容忍性呢？
So what do I mean by error tolerant?
我觉得你们已经体验过错误容忍性的一个方面，就是在量化中。
So I think you already experienced one part of error tolerance is in quantition.
你引入了一些错误，但模型还是可以工作的，对吧？
You introduced some errors, but the model can still work, right?
嗯，只要你不要偏离太远，
Uh, so as long as you don't deviate too far,
我觉得模型还是会以某种方式收敛的。好的，这就是大致的想法。
I think the model will converge in some way. Okay, that's the idea.
所以在评分设计中，也是同样的情况。
So in grading design, that's the same case.
基本上，你可以这样来思考评分设计。
So basically, you can think about grading design.
这里，我在做绿色强调，好吗？你正在爬一座山。
Here, I'm doing green accent, okay? You are climbing a hill.
对吧？
Right?
你可以用不同的路径爬这座山，对吧。
You can collab this hill using different paths, right.
假设你有一个完美的评分，那么你基本上就是一路
So assuming like you have a perfect grading, then you basically collab all the
爬到顶端，就像这样。
way up, right, like this.
好吗？你们都用最少的时间到达了顶峰，对吧？
Okay? And you all take the least time to reach reach the top, right?
但就像我说的，机器学习程序对错误有很强的容错性，梯度下降也是如此。
But like I said, machine learning program is pretty error tolerant green isn't is the same.
所以你可以像这样用不同的路径协作，对吧？
So you can collab with different paths like this, right?
你可以像这样稍微偏离一下，好吗？
You can deviate a little bit like this, okay?
就像这样，这样，这样，这样。
Like this, like this, like this, like this.
好的，你们可能多走了一些步，但最终因为梯度下降的特性，
Okay, you all take a little bit more steps, but eventually because of the nature of green isn't,
你们还是会到达山顶。
you are going to reach the top of the hill.
这意味着你不需要完全精确地使用
Okay. Which means that you don't how to exactly use the precise version
当前状态下计算出来的梯度。
of the gradient derived at the current state.
你可以用一个可能稍微有点错误的版本。
You can use probably slightly wrong version of it.
但只要你遵循一些条件，你仍然可以达到目标。
But as long as you follow some conditions, you can still get there.
好的。在这种情况下，人们基本上会这样做，
Okay. And with this situation, what people does is basically,
呃，我觉得这基本上解释了我刚才说的，对吧？
uh, I think this basically explain what I said, right?
所以你不知道如何遵循梯度线。
So you don't how to follow the grading line.
你可以稍微偏离一下，仍然能到达顶点。
And you can slightly debate, you still get the top.
在这种情况下，人们基本上想要放宽一致性模型的要求。
And with this one, people want to basically relax the um consistency model.
放宽一致性的一种方式就是我不要求一致性。
One way to relax the consistency is I don't how a consistency.
所以每个工作节点基本上都以自己的节奏计算。
So every worker will basically compute at their own pace.
我不会去关心其他参数或者梯度。
I don't bother to know other parameters or gradients.
我只是按照自己的节奏计算，不会进行更新。
I just compute at their own pace. I don't update.
I only update at, say,
100 ingredients or 200 ingredients.
In that way, you are doing much better because you don't how to compute,
you don't have to synchronize at every iteration gradients.
Okay. But the problem is then every worker will basically take
their own pass to update the parameters.
At some point, you just average the parameters, and it's likely that all workers are divided, okay?
So this is basically, uh, the case I explained.
So here, device one is the slowest.
So in this window time, device one only perform one iteration.
但在这个时间窗口内，设备二、三、四基本上执行了很多很多操作，
But in this window time, Device two and three, four, they basically perform many many interes,
并且它们之间没有任何屏障。
and there's no barrier between them.
好的，你只需要做你自己的工作。
Okay, you just do your own job.
显然这样做是行不通的，因为它违背了数据并行的初衷。
And this apparently doesn't work because it defeat the purpose of data parism.
你根本没有进行任何聚合操作。
You are not aggregate ingredits at all.
明白了吗？所以我们最终找到了一种折中的方法，
Okay? So what we ended up with is we find the middle ground between
介于强一致性和无一致性之间。
strong consistency and no consistency.
好的，这被称为SSP。
Okay. And this is called SSP.
它叫做钢性一致性。
It's called steel consistency.
什么是钢性一致性呢？
What do I mean by steel consistency?
在这里，我引入了一个额外的变量，就是静止性。
That is here, I introduce additional variable, which is stillness.
这个静止性具体描述了被拷贝的梯度或者参数有多“静止”。
And this stillness specifically characterize how steel the copied gradients is or the parameters.
我来给你举个例子。
So I'm going to give you an example.
这里，设备A和B都以相同的速度进行，并且会完成一次交互。
So here, device A and B, they all proceed with the same pace, and we'll finish intercon.
然后因为设备B稍微快一点，它会多进行几次交互，好吗？
And then because device B a bit faster, it goes interon more, okay?
还有另一个更快的设备。
And do another fast device.
我得到了更多的设备B，它甚至更快，对吧？
I got more and B, even faster, right?
你可以看到，在这个过程中，我没有进行同步。
And you can see during this process, I don't synchronize.
我只是让A、B、C按照各自的速度推进，进行各自的计算。
I just like the US ABC to proceed the pace, procedure competition.
但在某个时刻，设备B太快了。
But at some point, device B is too fast.
我发现最慢的工人是USA，最快的是USB，
I find that the slowest worker, which is USA and the fastest work which is USB,
他们之间已经有三步的差距了。
they already have three steps apart.
当这三步的差距超过了我的静止阈值时，
And when the three steps apart is basically exceeding my stills threshold,
我会告诉他们，你们应该停一下，稍微同步一下。
I'm going to tell them, you should stop and you guys should synchronize little.
明白了吗？很好。只要我们保持这个松弛窗口，
Okay. Does that make sense? Cool. As long as we maintain this relaxation window,
我们基本上可以大大减少阻塞，
uh, we can basically, greatly reduce the lumber,
就像整个教室的全局同步一样。
like global synchronization across the entire classroom.
所以我们就让他们继续做下去，你知道的，这就是所谓的网络阻塞，对吧？
So we just let them go and go, you know, uh this web block, right?
然后我们就让它继续下去。
And we just let it go.
我们就可以有效地减少，嗯，阻塞通信。
And we can effectively reduce the, um, lumber communication.
因此，呃，但我们仍然保留了一些类似地狱俱乐部的绿色口音。
Therefore, uh, but we still preserve some sort of like club in the hell right, green accent.
好的，确实如此。
Okay. And indeed,
我认为在神经网络出现之前，人们经常这样做，
I think back then before neuro networks, uh, people do this a lot,
这样可以加速分布式训练，而且可以证明，
okay to accelerate the distribute training and, um, and it can prove that basically,
如果你的模型收敛，实际上取决于静止度的数值。
if your model converges, it really depends on the value of stillness.
所以基本上，当静止度等于零时，你是在做强一致性，对吧。
So basically, when steels is equal to the zero you are doing strong consistency, right.
当静止度为无穷大时，你就没有一致性了。
When stillness is infinity, you have no consistency.
所以它其实是一个连续的谱。
So it's actually a continuous spectrum.
所以人们通过在不同的静止度和不同的模型上做了很多这种实验，
So people do a lot of this kind of experience by experimenting in
他们发现基本上这个静止度的区域是可以的。
different stis against different models, and they find that basically this region of Stines is okay.
但如果你超出了这个范围，你知道，你的模型就会崩溃。明白吗？
But if you go beyond this, you know, your model is going to break. Okay.
而且尽管有很多开放的人，人们还是证明了很多东西，
And people also prove a lot of despite the open by people,
他们对这个变得非常着迷，因为这是，
they become very fascinated about this because this is,
这里面有很多美丽的理论。
there are a lot of beautiful theory behind all that.
他们想要证明这些，并且想要发表。
Okay, they want to prove and they want to publish.
这是我引用的一个方程，好吗？
And this is one equation I quoted, okay?
我认为解释这个方程的方法其实很简单。
And I think the way to interpret this equation is pretty simple.
你可以忽略所有的符号。
You can ignore all the symbols.
好的，我来告诉你它的意思。
Okay, I'm going to tell you what it means.
它的意思是静态估计之间的差异和
It means that the difference between a stillist estimate and
真实的估计值可以被一个项所界定。
the true estimate can be bounded by a term.
而这个项基本上是静止性的一个函数。
And this term is basically a function of the stillness.
好的。这意味着只要你的静止性不是太大，
Okay. That means that as long as your stillness is not too large,
我认为你就能达到最优。
I think you are going to achieve the optimal.
是的。就像我说的，这还是一个非常活跃的研究领域，
Yeah. Okay. Like I said, this is a very active area of research and
现在还有很多人在做这方面的研究。
people are still doing this today.
如果你查阅一些分布式计算的理论性工作，人们也在做这些事情。
Okay. If you check slightly more theoretical work in distribute machining, people are doing this.
但问题是，这在你的网络中效果并不好。
But the problem is, this does not work well in your networks.
嗯，因为就像我说的，如果你看这个方程，为了得到这个结果，你必须做出
Uh, because like I said, if you look at this equation, in order to get here, you have to make
很多关于你的目标的假设。
a lot of assumptions about your objective.
比如说，必须确定目标函数有一些凸性特征，
For example, it has to be certain, there are some convex characteristics about the objective,
并且你必须始终按照给定的学习率进行梯度更新。
and you have to perform grade always given learning rate.
但你可能知道，在深层网络中，很多事情是无法被证明的，对吧？
But you probably know that in deepen network, a lot of things cannot be proved, right?
而且，人们在这方面也无法取得任何理论上的进展。
And, um, people are not able to make any theoretical progress on this.
从经验上看，当你把这些单元应用到
And empirical, when you apply this units into,
内部网络时，我觉得效果并不是很好。
uh internar networks, I don't think it works pretty well.
好的。关于这部分有问题吗？
Yeah. Okay? Any question about this part?
很好。这基本上就是主服务器的内容。
Cool. That is basically primary server.
我认为关于主服务器还有很多其他问题，就像你们已经提到的那样，
I think there are a lot of other issues about prime server like you already mentioned,
有一些问题，但我给你们布置了阅读材料，你们可以查阅那篇论文。
there are some for issues but I think I give you a reading, and you can check on that paper.
另一种实现数据并行的方法，基本上就是这样，或者说是归约，对吧？
So another way of implementing, um, data parism is basically like this or reduced, right?
你基本上是在所有工作节点之间执行一个环形归约操作。
You basically perform a ring or reduce across all workers.
这实际上就是我们现在所采用的方法。
And this due is basically what we have today.
这是目前最常用的归约方案。
This is the most commonly used, um, scheme for performing or reduce.
好，前提是系统要支持。
Okay, providing the system support.
就像我说的，这是最流行的归约接口之一。
Like I said, this is one of the most popular reduce interface.
你要做的就是导入torch.distributed，导入DDP。
And what you do is basically you import this torch the disc, you import DDP.
然后你初始化一个进程组。
And then you initiate a process group.
你们的作业里会有这个，你们要去做这个。
You have this in your homework, you're going to do this.
你基本上就是在所有进程、所有线程之间声明rank。
You basically declare the ranks between all the processes all threats.
然后对于每个rank，你都要声明一个模型，对吧，因为你要为每个rank、每个线程复制模型。
And then for each rank, you are going to declare a model, right, because you are going to replicate
你会为每个rank、每个线程复制模型。
the model for each rank for each thread.
基本上你要做的就是进行训练。
And what you do is basically you perform the training,
我觉得在训练这一步的背后，基本上他们会帮你做reduce操作。
and I think behind the strain step is going to basically, they will perform reds for you.
关于reduce再多说一点历史吗？
A little bit more history about reduce?
它最初是在一个叫Harwood的框架中实现的，这个框架是Uber开发的。
It was initially implemented in a framework called Harwood, and this one is by Uber.
好的。Uber在某些分布式系统方面曾经做得非常好。
Okay. Uber was pretty good at sometime imagyemergen systems.
大概是在2015年左右。
And roughly in 2015.
现在如果你去查，这个Hord在Github上还有一万多个star。
Okay. And this Hord, if you still check, it has more than ten k starts on Github today,
后来，我记得在HR Word那个时代，还没有像Nick和CCO这样的库。
later, I think, at the time of HR Word, you don't have abraries like Nick and CCO.
你只有像MPI这样的库。
You only have library like MPI.
这就是你在作业中使用它的原因。
That's why you use in your homework.
好的。但就像我说的，MPI是用于
Okay. But like I said, MPI is for
CPU，而Niko是用于DPU的，明白吗？
CPU and Niko is for DPU. Okay?
后来，我认为媒体开始意识到这种连接将会流行起来，
And later, I think media start realizing that this connect is going to take off,
他们基本上有一支非常强大的Koda工程师团队来实现NCL。
and uh, uh, they basically have a very strong team of Koda engineers implement NCL.
我认为这个NCL现在基本上已经成为
Uh, I think this NCL no essentially become the default back for performing any type
在GPU之间进行任何类型连接通信的默认后端。
of connective communication between GPUs.
明白吗？它被ODM高度优化了。
Okay? It's highly optimized by ODM.
这是ODS模式之一。
And this is one of the ODS modes.
顺便说一下，这也证明了ODS库存的合理性。
This justifies the ODS stock, by the way.
后来当Niko离开时，
And later when Niko takes off,
我认为Petrog开始采用这个Nichols，并且他们建立了这个GDP。
I think Petrog start to adopt this Nichols and they build this GDP.
由于Petrog的流行，
Due to the popularity of petrog
我觉得大家基本上都从Word转向使用Petros原生的DDP接口了。
I think people basically move away from Word to use Petros native DDP interface.
好吗？还有一件事，
Okay? And one more thing
我想提到datapoism，因为现在所有的数据部分都是用
I want to mention about datapoism is because now all the data parts are implemented using
ORD AD有一个很糟糕的问题，就是它不具备容错性，对吧？
ORD AD has a very bad thing that's not fault tolerant, right?
因为当你执行ORD时，你必须调动所有的工作节点来
Because when you perform ORD, you have to mobilize all the workers to
执行那个环形通信。
perform that ring in communication.
如果有一个工人失败了，那么这个De也会失败。
And if one worker failed, then this De will fail.
这意味着due不是容错的。
Which means that due is not a fault tolerant.
如果你把Ds和primary sur进行比较，你会发现primary
And if you compare Ds to primary sur you'll find that primary
SR更具容错性，对吧？
SR is more fault tolerant, right?
因为你可以有不同的份额，有不同的工人。
Because you can have different shares, you have different workers.
所以如果有一个工人失败了，你依然没问题，你可能还有补救的方法，但在dus里就没有。
So I one worker field, you're still good, you probably have some way to remedy, but in dus, no.
好吗？但看起来在图像学习系统中，人们并不关心容错。好吧。
Okay? But it seems that image learning system, people don't care about fault tolerance. Okay. Yeah.
至少在我过去五年的经验中是这样的，没错。
That's what I at least in my past five years of experience, yes.
是的。但如果你谈论大数据处理，谈论数据库，
Yeah. But if you talk about big data processing you talk about database,
我认为容错是一个相当大的问题。
I think for tolerance is a pretty big issue.
是啊，大家都在谈论这个。
Yeah, everybody talks about that.
是的。好吧，好吧，有一个讨论点，如你所见，呃，我想指出的一件事其实是，
Yeah. Okay. Okay, one discussion is, as you can see, uh, one thing I want to point out is actually,
2010到2020年，我认为正如我说的，人们也发表了超过一千篇论文，
2010-2020, I think people publish, like I said, people also published more than 1,000 papers on
主要是在分布式梯度下降的主服务器上，就是那个研究方向。
primary server on distributed green descent, right on that studs thing.
但在某个时刻，Ad就接管了。
But at some point, Ad just takeover.
或者做非常简单的事情，没有容错，没有一致性。
Or du very simple thing, no fault tolerance, no consistency.
所以基本上，就是在实现、在编写强内核的代码，对吧？
So basically, just implementing just coding, strong kernels, okay?
所以我想问你为什么。
So I want to ask you why.
想一想，为什么？为什么会这样？
Think about this, why? Like why?
就像学术界总是这样，他们把某件事做得很复杂，结果更简单的东西反而占了上风，对吧？
Like Academia always do this, they grand something so hard and something simpler takeover, right?
我觉得一个原因就像我说的，或者说du很简单。
I think one reason is like I said, or du is simple.
我觉得业界真的喜欢简单的东西。
I think industry really like simple things.
好的。第二个原因，其实是因为硬件。
Okay. Second, it's really because of hardware.
就像我刚才说的，一开始，人们引入这种一致性
So like I said, at the beginning, uh, the reason people introduce this consistency on
这种主服务器-客户端架构，是因为他们假设通信会
this primary server client architecture is because they assume the communication is going to
成为瓶颈，对吧？
be a bottleneck, right?
他们引入一致性，是因为他们想减少大量同步，而减少
And, they introduce consistency because they want to reduce lumber synchronization and reducing
大量同步就等于减少通信。
lumber synchronizing equals to reducing communication.
但在某个时刻，AD刚刚推出了一项新硬件技术，叫做unveilink。
But at some point, AD just shape a new hardware technology called unveilink.
unveilink基本上就是，只要你在一个带有GPS的盒子里训练模型
Unwilink is basically as long as you train a model inside of one box with GPS you
基本上拥有几乎无限的带宽。
basically have almost infinent bandwidths.
一旦这成为现实，那么主错误的价值基本上就会消失。
And once this becomes a fact, then the value of prime error basically get
因为通信并不是关于瓶颈的问题。
lost because communication is not about neck.
Wing 基本上解决了通信中的通信问题。
Wing basically save the communication address the communicing problem.
你可以只用最简单的方式来完成通信，无论是什么方法。
And you can just basically use fact whatever is the
最简单的方式其实就是 orgs。
simplest to perform that communication, which is orgs.
但就像我说的，当我们进入多并行的时候，
But like I said, when we move on to
通信又会变成另一个问题，为什么呢？
Multipoism then communication will become another problem, why?
因为以前我们做数据并行时，只是在一个盒子里扩展到多个 GPU，有 wink。
Because previously when we do data parism we just scaled to GPS inside one box where we have wink.
但现在模型的规模又爆炸式增长了，
But now model size explode again,
模型规模变成了1750亿。
Model size becomes like 175 billion.
那你就必须要扩展到不止一个节点，对吧？
Then you have to scale beyond one node, right?
在两个不同节点之间，你就没有主节点了。
Beyond between two different nodes, you don't have a meink anymore.
那么通信就成了另一个问题。
Then communication becomes another problem.
这基本上引出了下一个话题，Mdpism。
That basically brings us to the next topic, Mdpism.
我得换一下幻灯片，给我一分钟。
I have to switch slide. Give me 1 minute.
好的，嗯，是的，我们已经讲完了数据并行。
Okay. Um, yeah, we finish data partism.
但数据并行仍然是非常常用的方法。
But still, data paris is a very commonly adopted thing.
我不是说它被重复了。
I'm not saying it's being duplicated.
我只是说主副本被重复了。
I'm just saying primary sur is being duplicated.
但实际上，你需要将数据并行与其他类型的多重并行结合起来。
But in reality, you have to combine data pism with other sort of multiparism.
现在我们来谈谈多重并行。
And now let's talk about Multipism.
好吗？我们讨论多重并行的方式，基本上是从互操作并行开始的，然后我们尝试
Okay? And the way we talk about Muliparism basically we start with interop partism and we try to
推导出一些关于如何优化互操作并行的数学理解。
derive some mathematical understanding of how to optimize inter partism.
然后我们尝试把这些理解映射到各种
And then we try to map this understanding with all sorts of,
呃，人们为此构建的系统实现上。
uh, system artifacts people build for this.
希望我们下周能完成互操作并行，然后我们会讲内部并行。
Hopefully, we finish Intern next week we'll do intra.
好的。所以我希望大家还记得互操作并行的目标或定义。
Okay. So I hope everyone still remember the goal or the definition of intero partism.
比如我给你一个神经网络，就像幻灯片上的这个计算图，还有一组设备，
So if I give you a neural network as this computer graph on this slide and also a set of devices,
设备一、二、三、四，比如说GPU，然后我让你来划分，呃，
device one, two, three, four, uh, for example, GPUs, and I ask you to partition, uh,
把这个计算图分配到这些设备上，然后最直接的方法是什么？
this computing graph onto these devices and then what's the most straightforward way?
是的，我可以像这样直接划分，对吧？可以吗？
Yeah, I can just partition, right, like this. Okay?
我就是划分，对，我只需要数节点的数量。
I just partition. Yeah, I just count number nose.
我尽量确保每个设备上的节点数量差不多，对吧？
I try to make sure each note each device has almost equal number of node, right?
这是一种划分方式，嗯，嗯，嗯，在这里我要介绍
And this is one way of partition, um, um, um, and here, I'm going to introduce
一个新的概念，在划分中？它叫做阶段（stage）。
one new concept in inter partismo? It's called stage.
基本上，我把这个原始的计算图划分成四个阶段，然后我希望
So basically here, I partition this original como graph into four stages and I like
每个设备负责一个阶段。
each device to hold one stage.
一个阶段基本上就是原始图的一个子图的一部分，明白吗？
And one stage is basically a part of a subgraph of the original graph, okay?
这就是一个阶段。好的，一旦我完成了这个划分，我就可以开始问你了，对吧？
It's a stage. Okay. Once I finish this partition, I can start asking you, right?
那我要怎么问你呢？我可以这样问你，对吗？
So how to ask you. So I can ask you in this way, okay?
那么实际上要问你这个pion近网络，我们该怎么做，因为我们
So to actually basically ask you this pion near network, what do we do, Because we
把第一阶段放在了设备一上，对吧？
put the first stage on Device one, right?
所以我们也把输入给了设备一，我们从设备一开始。
So we also give the input to the device one. We start from device one.
好吗？我们让你设备一，得到第一阶段的输出，对吗？
Okay? We ask you device one, to get the output of stage one, right?
然后我们让设备一把这个输出一转发给设备二，对吧？
And then we forward device one to forward this output one to Device two, right?
在这里，如果你还记得，我们必须做一次同步，我们需要通信，
And here, if you still remember, we have to do a sens we have to communicate,
但这是点对点通信。好的。
but it's B to B communication. Okay.
就像我说的，第一阶段的输出张量会被传输到设备二，
Uh, like I said, the output tensor of stage one will be transferred to device two as
因为第二阶段的输入需要第一阶段的输出。
the input of stage two requires the output.
现在，数据传输所花费的时间通常很少，因为我们只在两个阶段的阶段边界处传递阶段输出。
Now that the time spent on the data transfer is typically small because we only communicate
然后我们要做的，基本上就是继续这个过程。
stage outputs at the stage boundaries between two stages.
我们让第二阶段执行并获得输出，然后继续向前传递。
And then what we do is basically we continue this.
好吗？这很清楚，也很简单。
We let Stage two to execute and get the output and we forward forward.
最后，我们在设备四上运行第四阶段，并获得损失的输出，
Okay? This is pretty clear, simple.
比如说，整个新网络的输出。
And finally, we run Stage four on device four and we get the output of the loss,
好的。那么在关于流水线并行的文献中，我们刚才描述的执行过程
for example, the whole new network.
通常会被可视化成这样一个时间线。
Okay. So in the literature about intero partism the execution, we described just now is
这里，这个Y轴基本上代表的是设备。
basically often visualized as this timeline. Okay?
这里，这个Y轴基本上表示的是设备。
So here, uh, this Y access is basically the devices.
好吗？这个访问是有时间的。
Okay? This access is time.
好吗？这样我们就可以可视化执行过程。
Okay? So we can visualize the execution.
我刚才在这个图上描述的就是这个调度。
The schedule I just described on this figure.
好吗？所以，呃，前一页幻灯片上的执行看起来就是这样的，对吧？
Okay? So, uh the execution on the previous slide is looking like this, right?
所以设备一请求设备、设备、设备四。那么问题是什么？
So device one ask device device device four. So what's the problem?
你看，又有一个气泡，对吧？
You see, there's a bubble bubble again, right?
基本上，想一想。
Basically, think about it.
我们总是在和气泡作斗争。
I paran, we are always fighting bubble.
好吗？所以剩下的灰色区域表示设备处于空闲状态，我们通常称之为气泡。
Okay? So the remaining gray area indicates the device being idle and we typically call them bubbles.
好的。这个气泡的存在是因为数据依赖关系。
Okay. This bubble exists because of the data dependency between
不同设备上有不同的阶段。
different stages on different devices.
比如说，设备二需要输入设备一的输出，依此类推，你懂的，
Like device two requires the input of, uh, the output of device one and et cetera, you know,
正如我们所看到的，在任何时刻，在这个例子中，在任何时刻，
and as we can see, at any given moment, in this case, at any given moment,
只有一个设备在运行，对吧？
there's only one device running, right?
这意味着设备的利用率非常低，非常低。
And this means that the device utilization is super low, super low.
呃，为了量化这个设备利用率，呃，我们测量灰色区域的多少。
Uh, to quantify this device utilization, uh, we measure how much gray area.
嗯，我们测量流水线空泡在整个时间线上占据了多少。
Um we measure how much or the pipeline bubble will take on the uh whole timeline.
比如说，用这个acuton调度，
And for example, uh with this acuton schedule here,
流水线空泡的百分比就是这个数字。
the pipeline bubble percentage will be this number.
好吗？这个很容易理解，对吧？
Okay? This is pretty easy to understand, right?
所以基本上，你只需要看这一列，只有一个设备在运行。
So basically, you just look at this column and there's only one device running.
所以基本上，这个气泡就是D减去一个设备再除以D，非常糟糕。
So basically the bubble is D minus one device by D. Very bad.
好吧，你的MF会非常差，明白吗？
All right. Your MF is going to be terrible. Okay?
如果你这么做，非常危险。
If you do this, you know, very dangerous.
好的，明白。我想你明白我的意思了。
Okay. Cool. I think you got my point.
那么主要的提升方式——我们想要提升这个，对吧？
So the main way to improve so we want to improve this, right?
所以提升跨分区效率的主要方法
So the main way to improve the ascen efficiency for inter partism
基本上就是通过流水线处理不同的输入。
is basically through pipeline ASQonu different inputs.
那我们现在来看，输入A基本上就是在第一阶段进行流水线处理，对吧？
So let's see right now, the input, A is basically asq on stage one, right?
所以输入A完成之后
So after input A finishes
在第一阶段提问，在第二阶段开始处理。
Asking on stage one and start Sceving on stage two.
我们要做的是，同时因为第一阶段是空闲的，所以我们基本上可以
What do we do is, at the same time because stage one, uh, is idle, we can basically
像这样再加入另一个输入B，对吧？
fit another input B like this, right?
所以在这里，第二阶段处理输入A，而第一阶段可以接收另一个输入并开始处理。
So here, stage two, askeed input A and stage one can take another input and askew on it.
好的？我们可以把另一个输入B放到第一阶段，并且在处理A的同时处理B。
Okay? And we can fit another input B into stage one and as skewed at the same time
同时，输入A在第二阶段处理时，B也在第一阶段处理。
as input A skewed on stage two.
然后，下次，当输入进入第三阶段时，我们就可以把B交给第二阶段，
And again, next time, okay, input equals to stage three, then we can give B for B to stage two,
而第一阶段又可以接收一个新的输入C。
and we can at stage one to take another new input input
这就叫做流水线计划。
C. This is called pipe planning. Okay?
嗯，是的，我们只需要不断重复这个过程，就可以基本形成……
Um, yeah, we just repeat doing this and we basically form
一个流水线，这个流水线会问你，接下来会发生什么，对吧？
a pipeline and this pipeline ask you what goes on, right?
我们继续说下去。当流水线有多个输入时，流水线会产生气泡。
We'll go on. With pipeline in multiple inputs, then the pipeline bubble it
这可以简化为基本上那样的图形。
can be reduced to basically that figure.
只有在第一步时，我们只有一个设备。
Only the first step we only have one device.
但一旦流水线启动并开始运转，你会发现利用率会增加。
But once the pipeline starts and start rolling out, you can see the utility is going to grow.
有人能告诉我这里的利用率是什么吗？
Can anyone tell me what's the utility here?
方程。我来告诉你答案。
Equation. I'm going to give you the answer.
想一想，本质上就是这样，你不断地让流水线运转。
Think about that. Essentially, like this, you keep rolling the pipeline.
百分比气泡基本上是D减一除以D减一加N，这里的N是输入数。
The percentage bubble is basically D minus one divided by D, minus one plus N where N is the input.
好了，这样说有道理吗？
Okay. Does that make sense?
很好。我们聊完之后可以想一想这个问题。
Cool. Think about that, after we talk.
那么在这里，如果你看这个方程，你会发现一个非常有趣的现象，那就是
So here, if you look at this equation, you will find a very interesting phloma that is
N 是你要传送的木材批次数量。
N is lumber batches, you're going to pipeline.
从情感上讲，我们有无限的批次。
Emotionally we have infinite batches.
你可以假设我们有无限的批次，这意味着当 N 趋近于无穷大时，
You can assume we have inflint batches, which means that when N goes to infinity,
这个泡沫会逐渐消失，我们又会变得没问题，对吧？
this bubble is going to diminish and we are good again, right?
同意吗？有人不同意吗？
Agree? Anyone disagree.
我不同意。好吧，我们不会再变得没问题了，好吗？
I disagree. Okay, we are not going to be good again, okay?
我向你保证，好吗？所以看起来如果你有无限批次，嗯，我们又没问题了。
I assure you, okay? So it seems that if you have infinite batches, um, we are good again.
但这只是针对推理阶段，对吧？
But this is only for inference, right?
因为在推理时，假设你有无限批次，你基本上只做前向传播，对吧？
Because in inference of assuming you have infinite batches, you basically perform forward, right?
然后你又没问题了，是的。
And you are good again, yes.
这就是为什么PublmPis在推理时表现不错的原因。
That's why PublmPis pretty good for inference.
如果你做推理，你可以用这个publiparis，完全没问题。
If you do inference, you can do this publi paris, there's no issue.
你只会有一点点延迟，但这个延迟基本上会被消除。
You only suffer a little bit bubble, but that bubble is basically what diminished.
但就像我说的，根本问题是我们需要做训练，对吧？
But like I said, the fundamental problem is we need to do training, okay?
那这里发生了什么呢？
And so what happened here?
所以，嗯，流水线处理不同输入批次在训练时并不简单适用。
So Okay, um, Pipeline different input batches doesn't simply work for training.
原因是对于神经网络训练，在前向传播之后，嗯，然后，嗯，
The reason is that for new network training after the forward pass, um and then um,
基本上在我们获得特定输入的损失之后，
and basically after we getting the loss on the specific input,
我们需要执行反向传播，对吧？
we need to perform a backward pass, right?
所以我们要做的是，嗯，我们需要执行反向传播来计算梯度
And so what do we do is, um, we need to perform the backward pass to calculate the gradient
并且在反向传播中，数据依赖关系是反过来的。
and the data dependency in the backward pass is reversed.
明白了吗？比如说，对于第二阶段，它需要第一阶段的输出
Okay? So for example, for stage two, it requires stage one's um output
来运行前向传播，对吧？
to run the forward pass, right?
但在反向传播中，第一阶段需要第二阶段的梯度信息来计算
But in the backward pass, stage one requires Stage two uh, grading information to calculate
当前阶段自己的梯度。
its own gradient on the current stage.
此外，在我们计算出梯度后，还需要用
And in addition, after we calculate the gradient, we need to update the neural network with
梯度来更新神经网络，然后开始下一个输入的前向和反向传播。明白了吗？
the gradient and then start the forward and backward pass of the next input. Okay.
所以在这种情况下，我们都会得到这个时间线，对吧？
So in that case, we all get this timeline, right?
这是一次反向传播。
This is a backward pass.
这里，我只有一个批次，明白吗？
Here, I only have one batch, okay?
这其实很容易理解。
And this is pretty easy to understand.
我只需要做和之前完全一样的事情。
I just do this exact the exact.
你可以看到有一个中间点，我需要进行一次参数更新。
And you can see there's a middle point where I have to update perform an oppment update.
这就是为什么我要进行更新。
That is why I have update.
好的，这部分我们没问题吧？
Okay, we are good with this one, right?
嗯，所以在这种情况下，时间线的安排会像图中那样，
Um, so in this case, screening timeline will be like in
因为前向和反向的依赖关系，执行顺序会从设备一到设备四，
figure because of the forward and backward dependency, the execution will be from device one to
然后再从设备四回到设备一，然后我们再进行操作。
device four and then from four to device one, um, you know, and then we perform
绿色更新，并在下一个输入中继续。
a green update and continue on the next input.
如你所见，这里的流水线效率仍然非常低。
As you can see, the pipeline efficiency here is still very
设备大部分时间都处于空闲状态。
low and device are being idle, most of the time.
好的。
And, Okay.
我们会为此提出一个解决方案。
And we are going to have a solution for this.
但在那之前，我想，这部分是理论内容，关于流水线空闲的问题。
But before that, I want to probably, this is a theory part, okay, for papel empaism.
但我想结合一些实际案例，看看人们在训练模型时是怎么做的。
But I want to ground this on some real works that people doing in training their models.
好的，我们会逐步揭示更多填补这些空闲的方法。
Okay. And we gradually, like reveal more and more solutions to how to fill those bubbles.
好的。
Okay.
之前有不少工作都专注于减少流水线中的空闲气泡。
So there's quite a few previous works focus on reducing the pipeline bubbles,
因此，通过减少气泡，他们可以增加设备的添加，对吧。
and, uh, therefore, by reducing bubble, they can increase the device addition, right.
我们通常把之前的工作分为三类。
And we generally categorize the previous work into three categories.
第一类叫做设备布局。
The first one is called device placement.
好吗？你可能读过这篇论文。
Okay? You probably read this paper.
这是一篇非常著名的论文，来自机器学习委员会，同样由JFD发表，是谷歌的论文。
It's a very famous paper from machining commitee, again, published by JFD, okay, from Google.
然后，嗯，第二类叫做同步流水线算法。
And, um Uh, and the second category is called synchronous, the pipeline algorithm.
第三类是异步的。
And the third category is a synchronous.
在这里，同步或异步，
And here synchronous or synchronous,
我觉得你已经理解了，因为我在数据并行时讲过，对吧？
I think you already get an understanding because I talk about that in data parism right?
所以同步意味着你有很强的一致性。
So synchronous means you have a strong consistency.
异步的意思是你尝试稍微放宽我的一致性要求，好吗？
And asynchronous means that you try to relax my consistency a little bit, okay?
然后我们都展示出来。好的。
And we all reveal. Okay.
首先，让我们来看一下这个设备的分配。
First, let's take a look at this device placement.
这里的目标基本上是把神经网络的分支切分成多个阶段，
The goal here is basically slice the branches of neural network into multiple stages
这样它们就可以同时计算了。
so they can be calculated concurrently.
比如说，如果这个神经网络可以被分解成这四个阶段，对吧？
So for example, if the new network can be decomposed into these four stages, right?
如果有一个新的看法在这里，好吗？
If there's a new looking on this, okay?
这里的Sg二和Std三是两个互不依赖的分支。
Here Sg two and Std three are two branches that do not depend on each other.
它们是并行分支。好的。我们基本上可以让你同时处理Std二
They are parallel branches. Okay. And we can basically ask you to Std two
和三，对吧？
and three in parallel, right?
如果我们希望了解这些方法的时间线，基本上就是这样的，对吧。
And if we wish you a the timeline of these approaches, um, we basically get this one, right.
所以基本上，你可以说在这个时间点，
So basically, um, you can say at this time points, uh,
设备二和设备三是并行执行的，因此我们有效地减少了空闲周期。
device two and three are executed concurrently, so we effectively reduce bubbles.
这样说有道理吗？很好。
Does it make sense? Cool.
这种设备分配的最大限制是它只适用于特定的新型网络。
The biggest limitation of this device placement is that it only works for specific new networks.
就像我说的，你必须有这种分支的数据结构。
Like I said, you have to have this kind of branching out data photograph.
比如说，它可以用于这个Inception模型，其中包含了
For example, it can work for this inception model, which includes branches of
不同尺寸的卷积分支。
different sizes of convolution.
这个Inception Wiser是在谷歌发明的一个非常著名的新型网络，好吗？
This inception wiser is a very famous new network invented at Google, okay?
它也可以用于对比模型，基本上，呃，
Um, and it can also work with contrastive models, which basically, uh,
包含两个分支用于两个输入。
includes two branches for two inputs.
这种对比模型在某个时期在coervon中非常流行。
And this contrastive model at some point is very popular in coervon.
好的。然而，它不能像其他一些
Okay. However, it cannot be used to accelerate model like other sort
卷积工作和transformers那样加速模型。
of conal works and also transformers.
这是bird。好，没有这种情况。
This is bird. Okay, no such case.
此外，正如你所看到的，你和我做这个时，设备利用率仍然很低，对吧？
And in addition, uh, as you can see, you and I do this, the device utilon is still quite low, right?
例如，当第一个和最后一个设备在运行时，
For example, when the first and the last device is running,
所有其他设备基本上都处于空闲状态。
all other devices become, um, basically idle.
好吗？所以设备分配基本上需要与其他流水线调度结合使用，
Okay? So device placement basically need to be combined with, um, um, other pipeline schedules,
这个我们接下来会讨论。
which we'll discuss next.
好的，另一种提高效率的方法叫做同步流水线并行。
Okay, another type of methods to improve efficiency is what we call synchronous pipeline parallel.
这里的基本思路是，我们修改流水线调度来提升效率，
Okay? The idea here is basically, we modify the pipeline schedule to improve efficiency,
但保持计算和收敛的语义完全一致，就像你
but keep the computation on the convergence semantically the same, exactly the same as if you
在单个设备上训练一样。
are training on a single device.
所以最早的相关工作，也是我给你们推荐阅读的非常著名的工作，就是GPipe。
So the very first work, okay, the very famous work which I gave you at reading is basically GPipe.
这里的G代表Google，没错，是Google发明的。
Okay? G stands for Google, again, invented by Google.
所以第一个流水线并行的工作就是GPipe。
Okay? So the first work was pipeline parison is GPipe.
主要思想是将输入批次进行切分。
The main idea here is to split the input batch.
这里我会用我刚才介绍的方法。
Here I'm going to use the one I introduced, okay?
我会把输入批次切分成微批次。
I'm going to split the input batch into micro baatches.
这里我用的是我自己的microbatch定义。
Here I use my definition microbtch.
希望你们不要感到困惑。
I hope you don't get confused.
我会把我的输入批次拆分成很多个microbatch，然后我们对这些microbatch进行流水线处理。
I'm going to split my input batch into many micro baatches then we perform
这就像是给这些microbatch上的流水线教学。
the pipeline as tuition for these micro baatches.
这和梯度累积非常相似。
It's very similar to the green accumulation.
但它是分布式的调度方式。
But it's a distributed orchestration.
我来给你们演示一下。基本上，因为整个输入批次的梯度可以
Let me show you. Basically, since the gradient of the whole input batch can be
分解为各个microbatch梯度的平均值，
decomposed into the main of the gradients of microbatches,
在梯度累积时，我们基本上可以把不同microbatch的梯度累积起来，
I gradient accumulation, and we can basically accumulate gradients
等所有microbatch都处理完后再一起更新。
into different microbatches and updated with altogether later once we finish a micro batches.
那我们这样说吧。比如说，我们把输入分成六个微批次，
So let's say this. So for example, let's say we split our input into six microbatches,
然后我们基本上可以这样运行前向传播。
then we can basically run the forward pass like this.
关于44个设备和六个微批次没有问题。
No problem about 44 devices, six micro baatches.
这里的问题是，当我们以流水线方式运行前向传播时，对于所有输入，
The problem here is when we run the four pass in pipeline fashion, for all inputs, we have to
我们必须保留所有中间激活值。
keep all the intermediate activations.
我们不能把它们丢弃，对吧？为什么？因为我们还需要进行反向传播，对吧？
We cannot through them right. Why? Because we need to perform backward, right?
我们必须保留它们。
We have to preserve them.
明白了吗？然后我们对所有微批次进行反向传播，就像这样，对吧？
Okay? And then we perform a backward pass for all micro baatches like this, right?
所以这里我已经准备好了微批次五，对吧？
So here I hold the microbtg five ready, right?
激活值已经计算出来了。
A activation computed.
然后我会在设备四上安排反向或微型批次五。
And then I schedule the backward or micro baat five on the device four.
接着我基本上开始对反向过程进行流水线处理。
And then I basically start pipelining the backward.
这有点像反向操作。
It's a kind of reverse figure.
最后，我们用累积的梯度来更新模型，
And finally, we update the model with the accumulated reading,
然后我们得到新版本的模型，并继续处理下一个批次。
and we get the new version model with, and we continue with the next batch.
显然，这个模式会重复进行。
Obviously repeat this pattern.
好的，有什么问题吗？
Okay. Any problem?
有。
Yeah.
你说的开销是什么意思？
What do you mean by overhead?
是的，那可以在我启动任务之前完成。
Yeah, that can be done before I launch a job.
是的。这是在运行时之前的事情。
Yeah. It's something before runtime.
是的。
Yeah.
这样说有道理吗？可以。我可以准备那个。
Does that make sense? Yeah. I can prepare that.
我可以做预计算的预处理，可以吗？可以。
I can do pre compute pre processing, Okay? Okay.
这里我要问另一个问题，非常重要。
Here I'm going to ask another question and very important.
那么在这种情况下，流水线气泡的百分比用数学形式怎么表示？
So in this case, what's the pipeline bubble percentage in mathematical form?
好的，我来给你一个公式。
Okay, I'm going to give you equation.
你应该先自己消化一下，让我说完。
You should internalize a little bit. Let me finish.
好的。这是同样的事情，对吧？
Okay. So this is the same thing, right?
前向和后向是反过来的，气泡完全一样。
Forward backward is reverse, bubble is exactly the same.
请用Dmus one plus合并一个Dmus one设备。
Dmus one device by Dmus one plus, please.
对你来说，就是把所有东西合并成一个。
For you combine everything into one thing
你的内存不够。
You don't have enough memory.
是的，你的内存不够。
Yeah. You don't have enough memory.
即使你有足够的内存，如果你看这个等式，假设你可以做到。
Even if you have enough memory, you are going to if you look at this equation, assume you can.
假设你可以做到。那问题是什么？
Assume you can. What's the problem.
问题是你真的想减少你的泡泡数量。
The problem is you really want to reduce your bubbles.
如果你把你的微批次合并成一个更大的批次，问题是泡泡数量会减少。
And if you combine your microbatches into a bigger battery, the problem is is going to decrease.
之前，微批次的数量等于六。
Previously, have a lumber microbaty equal to six.
所以如果你把微批次合并成一个，你就把它减少到三。
So if you consolidate the microbatch into one, you reduce it to three.
一旦你把它减少到三个，会有什么问题？
And once you reduce it to three what's the problem.
你的气泡会增加，对吧，因为这个数字减少了。
Your bubble is going to increase, right, because this number is decreased.
所以气泡会增加。
So the bubble is going to increase.
你的设备将有更多空闲时间。
Your device will have more atle time.
当然。那么你说的更快更新是什么意思？
Sure. So the sooner What do you mean by update sooner?
是的，你会更快地进行更新。
Yeah, you are going to update sooner.
是的，周期会变短，这些气泡的百分比会增加。
Yeah, the cycle is going to be shorter, the percentage of these bubbles is going to increase.
是的。还有其他问题吗？
Yeah. Any other question?
有。
Yeah.
是的，是的，非常好的问题。
Yeah. Yeah. Very good question.
我可以告诉你，这是有上限的。
I can tell you there's a limit.
好的。实际上，我在讲内存那一部分的时候提到过这个问题。
Okay. And actually, I talked about this somewhere during the memory section.
所以请你想一想，好吗？
So think about this, okay?
你被要求用批量大小为一千来训练模型，好吗？
You are locked to train a model with a badge size equal to one K. Okay.
基本上，这是超参数调优的结果。
So basically, that's a result from hyperprimy tuning.
也就是说，用批量大小为一千训练会带来最好的收敛效果。
That is training with the basis equal to one K will give you the best convergence.
假设这个条件无法满足。
Assuming that that's not available.
这是一个常量，你必须这么做。
That's a constant, you have to do that.
如果你用流水线并行，最好的结果就是
And then if you do Pip parism the best you can do is basically you
你用一千个微批次来训练，对吧？
train with 1,000 microbatches, right?
你用基数为一来训练1000个微批次，这个气泡
You use the basis equal to one to train with 1,000 microbates and this bubble
会被最小化，对吧？
is going to be minimized, right?
因为这个就在这里。
Because this one is here.
但问题是什么？有人能说说吗？
But what's the problem? Can anyone tell?
是的。
Yeah.
没错。
Exactly.
因为每次你增加微批次，都会减少有效批次大小。
Because every time you increase microbaties, you are going to decrease the effective body size.
那么减少有效批次大小会有什么影响？
So what's the effect of decreasing effective body size?
你会减少你的matamo大小，对吧？
You are going to reduce your matamo size, right?
一旦你减少了mamosize，你的GPO，原始强度就会降低。
Once you reduce the mamosize, your GPO is going to be the original intensity is going to decrease.
所以你减少了较弱的泡沫，但你也降低了AI的表现。
So you decrease lamer bubbles, but you also decrease the AI.
最终，当你在像Open这样的公司训练大型模型时，这其实是一个非常艰难的决定，
Eventually, when you train arg models in company like Open At this is a pretty hard decision that
他们必须确定微批次的大小和有效批次大小。
they have to figure out the microbdy sizes and effective body size.
微批次数量。他们必须在
Number microbachies. They have to strike a balance between
AI和设备利用率之间找到平衡。这样说有道理吗？
AI and deviszon. Okay, does that make sense.
我很高兴你问这个问题，因为我本来就打算讲这个。
I'm glad you ask because I'm going to cover that anyway.
好的，明白了吗？很酷。这条公式非常重要。
Yeah. Okay? Cool. This equation is pretty important.
你需要记住，如果你做流水线并行，你的设备利用率
You need to remember, if you do pipeline partism, your device utilization is
是微批次数量的函数。
a function of lumber microbches.
你想提高这个数值，但不能提高得太多。
Okay? You want to increase that, but you cannot increase too much.
好的。那么在这种情况下，pop bubble 百分比就是这个公式。
Okay. Okay, so in this case, the pop bubble percentage is this equation.
根据原始 Pip 论文的实验结果，
And from the experiment results of the original Pip paper,
我们可以看到，仅仅使用这个 depip 调度，实际上的并行效率已经相当不错了。
we can see that with only this depip schedule, uh, the parallel efficiency is actually pretty good.
好吗？而且当 lumber microbt 很大的时候，我们几乎可以实现线性加速，
Okay? And we can achieve almost linear speed up when the lumber microbt is uh large,
就像我说的，因为当 lumber microbt 很大时，你的 ti 也很高。
like I said, because when lumber microbt is large, your ti is high.
明白了吗？
Okay?
现在，我要告诉你关于 Poplin 囚徒问题更复杂的一些内容。
Now, I'm going to tell you even more complicated problem about Poplin prison.
好吗？但是 GPipe 内存使用的一个重要问题。
Okay? So but one important issue of GPipes memory usage.
记住，每次你进行计算时，最好是在前向传播阶段。
Remember, every time when you perform the commutation, it's better on the forward pass.
对于一个 microba，你必须保留它的激活值。
For a microba you have to preserve its activations.
好吗？所以每个设备的GPip调度可以在这个图中可视化。
Okay? So the per device of the GPip schedule can be visualized in this plot.
好吗？而这部分其实就是一个内存，这部分其实就是一个内存，
Okay? And this part is a memory that is basically this part is a memory that
主要用来存储电机参数。它是一个常量。
is basically used to store the motor parameters. It's a constant.
就像我说的，基本上它在整个前向和反向传播过程中都是激活的，对吧？
Like I said, basically it's active during the entire forward backward pass, right?
并且这是一个固定的。
And there's a fixed.
这是一个固定的开销，我们对此无能为力。
This is a fixed cost, and we cannot do much about it.
好吗？然而，这部分，这部分基本上是被中间激活所占用的，对吧？
Okay? However, this part, this part is basically occupied by the intermediate activations, right?
因为每当你引入更多的微批次时，你就会为那个微批次保存一份
Because whenever you introduce more microbatch, you are going to save one copy of
激活值的副本。
the activations for that microbatch.
所以在某个时刻，尤其是在最后一个微批次前向时。
So at some point, at some point, especially at the last microbat forward.
这个，基本上就是达到峰值，对吧？
This one, basically achieve peak, right?
然后你开始在这个microbatch文件上做反向传播。
And then you start doing backward on this microbatg file.
因为你做了反向传播，你得到了梯度，所以你可以释放激活所占的内存。
And because you do backward, you get the gradits so you can release the memory for the activations.
所以在某个时刻，你的内存占用会减少。
So at some point, you're going to decrease.
这就是为什么会是这样的，好吗？
That's why it is like this, okay?
有没有人发现这个根本性的矛盾？
Does anyone basically spot this fundamental conflict?
我说过，在那个公式里，
I said, in that equation,
我在前一页幻灯片展示过，你希望lumbomcrobtches尽可能大，
I showed in my previous slide, you want the lumbomcrobtches to be as large as
这样可以最小化设备的Id。
possible to minimize the device Id.
但从这个图你可以看到，如果我增加lambermcrobatches，情况就会变成这样。
But from this figure you can see, if I increase lambermcrobatches, this is like this.
它总会增长到某个点，让我的GPU内存爆炸。
It's going to always grow to some point where my GPU memory is going to explode.
这意味着这个调度方案是行不通的。
Which means that this schedule doesn't work.
虽然看起来很美观，但实际上完全不起作用。
It looks pretty beautiful but it doesn't work at all.
基本上，在峰值时，我们必须同时存储参数和
Basically, at the peak, we have to store the parameter as well as
所有输入微批次的中间激活值。
the intermediate activities for all input microbatches.
明白了。
Okay.
所以内存等于参数加上激活值乘以微批次数量。
So memory equals to perimeter plus activation times number of microbages.
我希望这个值大一些，以最小化空闲时间。
I want this to be large to minimize bubble.
但我也希望这个值小一些，以最小化峰值内存。
But I also want this to be small to minimize the peak memory.
这基本上是根本性的矛盾。
Basically fundamentally contradictory.
好的。酷，那解决方案是什么？
Okay. Cool, what's the solution?
确实是有一个解决方案的。
The indeed is a solution.
这就是为什么我们还要讨论这个问题。如果没有解决方案，
That's why we still cover problem meorith If there's no solution,
这就不会在课程中讲解了。
this is not going to be covered in course.
GPipe调度的一种优化叫做1f1b调度，即一次前向，
One optimization of GPipe schedule is a so called 1f1b schedule, one forward,
一次反向调度，它是对原始GPipe调度的一种重新排序。
one backward schedule, and it is a re order of the original GPipe schedule.
正如这个图所示，你可以看到，呃，如果你愿意，我强烈建议你回去，
And as shown in this figure, you can see, uh, if you go okay, I highly recommend you go back,
看看这个，然后你尝试自己玩一下这个游戏。
look at this, and you try to basically play this game by yourself.
你可以试着把每个气泡放到时间线上每个区块，自己动手试试。
You try to play how to place a bubble each block on this timeline, play by yourself.
并且，只要你假设前向和反向的时间完全相同，
And, as long as you assume the forward and bawd is exactly the same time,
你想要在GPP计划下搞清楚这个11b的情况，
you want to figure out this 11b under the GPP schedule,
它们在交互时的延迟完全一样。
they have exactly the same latency for interact.
唯一的区别是我基本上在玩这个游戏。
The only difference is I basically play this game.
我试着重新排序这一个、两个、三个、四个，不同颜色的1234。
I try to reorder this one, two, three, four, different colors 1234.
所以，你知道，上面和下面是不一样的。
So, you know, uh, the above and the bottom are different.
但这会造成巨大的差异。差别是什么？
But this creates a huge difference. What's the difference?
11b和G pipe之间的主要区别是，11b会
So main difference between 11b and G pipe is that 11b will
优先执行反向过程。
prioritize the execution of the backwards.
好的，记住，在我之前的，如果你看这个计划，我将安排
Okay. Remember, in my previous, um, if you look at this schedule, I'm going to schedule
这个流水线的执行一直到前向过程结束。
this pipeline execution all the way to finish of forward.
然后我开始反向传播。
And then I start backward.
但就像我说的，你必须承受那个内存峰值。
But like I said, you have to suffer that memory peak.
但在这里，只要我有一个准备好进行反向传播的小批次，
But here, as long as I have batch one microbtch that is ready to perform backward,
我就会调度反向传播。
I'm going to schedule the backward.
我会在某种程度上交错前向和反向传播，这样反向传播可以被优先处理。
I'm going to interwind forward and backward in some ways, so this backward can be prioritized.
那么为什么优先处理反向传播会更好呢？
So why prioritizing backward could be better?
因为如果你看这个，如果你只跟踪这个microbt zero，
Because if you look at this if you just track this microbt zero,
对，在这个时刻，内存就可以被释放了。
right, at this point, the memory can be released.
很不错，对吧？
Okay. Pretty nice, right?
是的，如果你看microbay one，在PIP调度中，最后一个microbg会……
Yeah. And if you look at microbay one, in the PIP schedule, the one, the last microbg will
这里会被问到，对吧？
be the one will be asked here, right?
但我重新排序了。我会在这里问你。
But I reorder it. I'm going to ask you here.
但是如果你检查这个，在这一点上，microbg one 的内存将会被释放。
But if you check this one, at this point, the memory for microbg one is going to
明白了吗？还不错吧？
be released. Okay? Pretty nice, right?
好的，你会破坏这种差异。
Okay, you'll spoil the difference.
所以，呃，基本上，我不知道怎么重复，对吧？
So, uh so basically, um I don't know how to repeat, right?
所以我们只需要尽早执行反向传播。
So we just need to perform backward as early as possible.
但是只要重新做一次，我们的迭代延迟是一样的，但内存表现好多了，
But just redo this, we have the same iterating latency, but our memory is much better,
如果我们用这个 one B 调度方式来可视化内存，内存就不会再增长了，
if we visualize the memory specifically with this one B schedule, the memory will no longer
一旦我们开始执行反向传播。
grow once we start performing backward.
每当我们进行一次前向传播时，我们会立即跟着进行一次反向传播，
Whenever we perform a forward pass, we will immediately follow with a backward pass that
这样可以释放前向传播中间激活所占用的内存。
can free the amount of memory occupied by the forward intermediate activions.
因此，内存使用量会在中间某处达到平台期，就像这样。
Therefore, the memory usage will plate somehow in the middle, like this.
它会在这里增长，然后趋于平稳，最后减少。
It will just grow here and then plateau and then decrease.
使用这种f1b调度，我们只需要在设备之间分配激活的份额，
And with this f1b schedule, we will only need to straw amber devices shares of activations,
而不是在微批次之间复制激活。
instead of amber microbatches, copies.
基本上就是把这个因子从微批次数量减少到设备数量。
So basically reduce this factor from amber microbatches to lumber devices.
你自己思考一下这个问题，好吗？
Think about this by yourself, okay.
你应该能够推导出这个公式，因为我会在考试中问到你。
You should be able to dive this equation because I'm going to ask you exam about this.
好吗？拜托了。
Okay. Please.
嗯哼。在大多数情况下，是的。
Uh huh. In most cases, yes.
是的，好的。尤其是当你想要最小化你的空闲时间时。
Yeah. Okay. Especially when you want to minimize your bubble.
是的，你必须使用相当大的微批量，批量微批量。是的。
Yeah, you have to use a pretty large micro badges, lumber microbges. Yeah.
好的。
Okay.
就像我说的，如果B，WiFi调度允许我们执行
So like I said, If B, the WiFi schedule allows us to perform
现在可以用无限数量的微批量进行流水线并行。
pipeline parison with infinite number of microbtes now.
好吗？现在，基本上就像你说的，
Okay? Now, I can basically, like you said,
我只需使用超大的微批量来减少设备空闲时间，
I use just super large microbates to diminish the device bubble,
但我不会因此而遭受超高的峰值内存。
but I won't suffer from a super high peak memory.
好吗？
Okay?
我认为这基本上是本次讲座中最重要的部分。
I think this is basically the most important part of this lecture.
就像我说的，这和B是目前用于双GBT的方法。
And like I said, this and B is the one adopted today for twin GBT.
好的。我觉得对于tA语言模型也是这样。
Okay. Uh, I think also for t A language model.
好的。
Okay.
实际上，我们还可以再深入一点。
Actually, we can still grand it a little bit more.
这会变得稍微复杂一些。
This is going to be a little bit more complicated.
我不会深入讲解，但如果你感兴趣，你可以自己深入研究，
I'm not going to dive deeper, but if you are interested, you can dive deeper on this, but
我会给你一些指引。
I'm going to give you pointers.
对f1b调度的进一步优化，基本上就是将
A further optimentation, of the f1b schedule is basically to slice
神经网络切分为更细粒度的流水线阶段，以减少流水线气泡。
the neural network into more fine grained pipeline stages to reduce pipeline bubble.
假设我们正在用四台设备训练一个有八层的新网络。
Let's say we are training a new network with eight layers on four devices.
之前，我们会把连续的层聚合成四个阶段，
Previously, we cluster contiguous layers to form four stages,
每台设备基本上负责一个阶段。
and each device will basically responsible for one stage.
所以我们有了一种新的调度方式，叫做interwine 11b。
So we have a new schedule called interwine 11b.
在interwine 11b调度中，我们会把多个阶段放在同一个设备上。
And in the interwineO B schedule, we put more than one stage onto a single device.
具体来说，我们可以让每一层成为一个阶段，然后把第一阶段和第五阶段放在设备一上，
Specifically, we can let each layer be a stage and then put stage one and stage five on device one,
第二阶段和第六阶段放在设备二上，依此类推。就像这个图所示。
and stage two, and stage six on device two, and so on. Like this figure shoot.
这种方法的主要好处是，单个阶段的延迟，
The main benefit of this method is that the latency, a single stage, the latency
单个阶段的延迟变得更短。
of a single stage becomes shorter.
因此，例如，设备二只需要等待一半的时间就可以开始执行。
Therefore, for example, device two only need to wait half of the time to start excusing
而不是等待整个两层完成。
instead of waiting for the entire two layers.
好的。
Okay.
如果我们进一步在时间线上可视化执行过程，可以看到新的调度方式
If we further visualize the execution, in a timeline, we can see that the new schedule
进一步减少了流水线的空闲期。
further reduce the pipeline bubble.
你只需要对比一下这个。
You just need to compare this.
好的。就像我说的，
Okay. And this one, like I said,
GPip 有延迟，而 WiFi B 和 GPip 有相同的内部延迟。
GPip has latency, and WiFi B has the same inter latency with GPip.
但如果你把 WIF 和 B 交错执行，就能减少这种延迟，速度会更快。
But if you do this interleave WIF and B, you are going to reduce this latency. You become faster.
好的。
Okay.
这种方法的缺点是，因为我们有更多的阶段，对吧，
And, and the downside of this method is, since we have more stages, right,
所以我们需要设备之间更频繁地通信。
so we need to communicate more often between devices.
好的，所以基本上你要付出通信的代价。
Okay. So basically, you pay a communicating cost.
而且由于通信代价对于互操作并行来说通常很小，我们可以
And since the communicating cost is typically small for interoperor partism and we can
基本上获得加速，是的，这没问题。
basically get speed up, yeah, it's fine.
好的，如果你想的话也可以，但这不是必须的，好吗？
Okay. And if you want to it's not required, okay?
我不会在考试中做这个，但如果你想证明这一点，你可以试试看。
I'm not going to do this in exam, but if you want to grant this, you can try to pass that.
是的，这非常复杂。
Yeah, it's very complicated.
嗯，是的，我没提到的另一个复杂性是，这非常难以实现。
Um, yeah, another complexity I didn't mention is this is very difficult to implement.
这种问题并行的一个关键难点是很难实现非常高效的实现。
One key this ti problem parism is very hard to provide a very efficient implementation.
调试也很难，尤其是当你在很多设备上运行这种问题并行的时候。
It's very hard to debug. Especially when you launch this kind of problem parism across many devices.
如果出现错误，你并不知道是在哪里发生的。
And if there's an error, you don't know where it happens.
好的。好的。有什么问题吗？
Okay. Okay. Any question?
如果你基本上试图去处理这个，
If you basically try to grind this,
我可以告诉你，这个泡沫基本上就是这块木材，你可以看到，系数在哪里结束。
I can tell you the bubble is basically this lumber and you can see, where are the factor end.
好的。还有更多内容。
Okay. And there are more.
我不会全部讲完。我觉得大家已经在很认真地评分了。
I'm not going to cover. I think people are grading this pretty hard.
好的。
Okay.
那我们继续下一个词。
Then let's move on to next word.
下一个词是 TerraPp。
So next word, TerraPp.
Tara pup 基本上是一种用于激进模型的流水线部件，比如 TPT 语言模型。
Tara pup is basically a pipeline parts work to aggressive models, for example, TPT language models.
就像我说的，大多数稳定的艺术语言模型基本上都是变换器架构。
And, like I said, most stable art language models are basically, uh, transformer architecture.
如果我们用变换器来评估像这样的联合概率，
And if we use the transformer to evaluate probative of syndem like this,
基本上猫是最好的，我们首先会建模猫的概率，
um, basically cats are the best, and we will first mod probability of cats
条件是一个特殊的标记，也就是序列的起始，这样可以吗？
conditional on a special token, start off sequence, which is this okay
然后建模猫的概率，再是R，然后是最好的，最后我们以US结束。
then mod probability of cat and then R and then the best, and then we stop with the US.
这就是自回归模型。
This is autoregressive model.
在这里，我们有一个关键的观察点，就是一个输入标记的计算，
Um, so here, one key observation we have is, uh, the computation of one input token,
只依赖于前面的标记，而不依赖于后面的标记。
only depends on the previous token, but not the future tokens.
这就是我们所说的自回归。
This is what we mean by auto regressive.
比如说，当我们计算单词“there”的概率时，呃，
Okay? For example, when we calculate the probability of the word there, uh,
模型只关注“cats R”这两个词，但它并不依赖于
the model only looks at cats R, these two words, but there's no dependency on
最佳的、后续的词语。
the best, the following words.
那么为什么这很重要呢？
So why is it important?
基本上，在这个流水线并行中，我们的做法是
So basically in this trap pilin parison, the way we do is we use
利用这个特性在序列中执行流水线操作。
this property to perform pipe laning within a sequence.
那我们具体怎么做呢？比如在这里，我们可以让第一个 token 在设备一上运行。
So what do we do is for example here, we can not the first token run on device one.
好的，先运行它，然后把结果发送到设备二。
Okay. Run it first, and then we send the results to device two.
与此同时，让第一层去运行第二个 token。
Meanwhile, well the first layer to run a second token.
记住，看看这个区别。
Remember, look at this difference.
这里我让这个层级阶段处理一个 token，一旦完成，我就会
Here I this layer stage to take one token, once I finish it, I'm going to
把这个活动转发到这一层。
forward this activity to this layer.
同时，我要去这个变换层再取一个标记。
Meanwhile, I'm going to this transform layer to take another token.
我们不能这么做的原因是因为现在我们在做语言模型。
The reason we can't do this is because now we are doing language models.
我们有一个序列输入。像这样。
We have a sequence input. Like this.
一旦你看到它两步，你知道我接下来要做什么吗？
Once you see it two steps, you know what I'm going to do next?
我要继续这样做。
I'm going to continue to do this.
像这样分成部分。好的。
Wall form partsme this, like this. Okay.
这基本上就是Trapap的思想。
This is basically the idea of Trapap.
我们可以做这种分部分的操作，但这只适用于语言模型。
We can do this kind of parts but this is only special to language models.
嗯。
Yeah.
这个工作的另一个关键优势是你只能将bicycle设置为1，
Another key this advantage of this work is you can only do bicycle equal to one,
这对于小模型来说并不是特别好。
which is not super good for small models.
好的。
Okay.
那我接下来要讲另一个工作。
Then I'm going to tell you another work.
好的。它叫做Chimera。
Okay. It's called Chimera.
好的。在我之前的课程讲座中，
Okay. And in my previous offering with lecture,
我没有讲这个工作，因为它非常复杂。
I don't cover this work because this is very complicated.
但今天，我必须讲一下。
But today, I have to cover it.
你知道为什么吗？因为TipsIk用的就是这个。
You know why? This is the one that is used in TipsIk.
好的。Deep six基本上使用了PipelHizon。
Okay. Deep six basically uses PipelHizon.
好吗？所以请花些时间来给这个打分，
Okay? So do spend some time grading this because
因为我之后在讲语言模型的时候会再回到这个内容。
I'm I'm going to come back to this when we start talking about language models.
明白了吗？
Okay?
Chimera 是另一项工作，试图进一步优化 1B 调度方式，
So Chimera is another work that try to further optimize the one B schedule,
假设我们有四条稳定的流水线和两个输入的微批次，如果我们用 11b 来调度它们，
let's say we have four steady pipeline and two input micro baatches if we ask them with 11b,
基本上我们会得到这个 11b 的调度方式。
we basically get this schedule, 11b.
好的，我们可以在这里看出来。
Okay. And we can find it out here.
如果你只看这个图，好吗？
If you just look at this figure, okay?
这个图没有很多微批次，但我们可以用它作为例子。
This figure does not have many microbges, but let's use as an example.
如果你看这个图，你可以看到，有一些空隙，对吧？
If you look at this figure, you can see, there are some bubbles, right?
这里，这里，这里，这里，这里。好的。
Here, here, here, here, here. Okay.
这些气泡看起来我们可以插入另一条流水线。
And these bubbles looks like we can insert another pipeline.
对吧？我们只需要做一条反向流水线，然后把asc插入这些气泡里。
Right? We just do a reverse pipeline, and we insert asc into these bubbles.
好吗？所以看看这个火焰图，我们可以看到我们发现可以进入
Okay? So so look at this fire, we can see that we find out we can enter
另一条11b流水线或者反向11b。
another 11b pipeline or reverse 11b.
更具体地说，嗯，如果我们也维护一条反向流水线，
So more specifically, um, if we also maintain a reverse pipeline,
换句话说，我们在
in other words, we start the pipeline on
设备四上启动流水线，然后在设备一上结束。
Device four and then finish it on device one.
基本上，我们放了两份模型参数，对吧？
Basically, we put two copies of the model parameters, right?
一份是从设备一到设备四。
One is from device one all the way to four.
另一个是设备四合一，明白吗？
The other is Device four all to one, okay?
我们基本上可以得到另一条流水线，
And we can basically get another pipeline with
有两个微批次，一个来自这里，另一个来自那里。
two micro baatches one from here, the other from here.
明白吗？如果我们合并这条流水线，基本上就能得到这种调度方式，就像这张幻灯片上展示的那样。
Okay? And if we merge this pipeline, basically get this kind of schedule, okay on this slide.
哦，抱歉，这是第二个气泡。
Oh, sorry, this is the second bubble.
如果我们把它们合并在一起，就会得到这个结果。
If we merge them together, we get this one.
你可以看到，这其实很聪明，对吧？
Okay, you can see this is pretty smart, right?
我们基本上做了前向和反向传播，但用奖励机制贯穿
We basically do a forward and backward, but using a rewards all over
所有设备，并且我们把所有内容都整合在一起，你可以看到气泡效应减弱了。
the devices and we put allom together, you can see atom bubble diminish.
我们可以最大化我们的利用率。
We can maximize our utilization.
好吗？有什么问题吗？
Okay? What's the problem?
你已经有了两份参数的副本，不是激活值。
You have two copies already parameters, not activations.
基本上，这意味着你必须浪费一些内存来存储两份参数副本。
Basically, which means that you have to waste some memory to store two copies of parameters.
嗯，在Deep sick之前，在大模型出现之前，
Um, before Deep sick, before the big models,
我认为这是一个大家无法接受的问题。
I think this is a problem that people do not accept.
但在某个阶段，人们不断扩展规模，不断扩展训练，直到像两个KTP那样。
But at some point, people continue to skill and skill to skill and skill training to like two KTPs.
那时候你会发现你有非常多的内存。
At that point, you find that you have many many memory.
你的内存多到可以负担两份参数副本。
You have so many memory that you are able to afford two copy of parameters.
这就是为什么Tip stake是一个胜利，对吧？
That's why Tip stake is a win, right?
Deep用一种方式来最小化dias bubble。
Deep uses one to minimize the dias bubble.
好的，今天我们就到这里。
Okay. Today, I'm going to stop here.
我觉得有很多内容需要你们慢慢消化一下，
I think there are so many contents that you have to digest a little bit,
下周我们会深入探讨更多内容。
and we are going to deeper and deeper next week.
好的，很棒，谢谢大家。
Okay. Cool. Thank you.